okay let's do some calculations
regarding the molar mass of a gas. if we
have a one point three one gram sample
of a hydrocarbon we vaporize it and it
is found to occupy two point zero liters
at 25 degrees Celsius and one point zero
atmospheres what is the gas we want to
identify this gas now we're gonna
probably need to use some information
regarding ideal gases to answer this
question so if you need to review ideal
gases go ahead and check out that
tutorial and when you're ready give this a try.
so we have our given information one
point three one grams 2.0 liters 25
degrees Celsius and 1 atmosphere so
we're definitely going to need to use
the ideal gas law in order to answer
this question
so that's PV equals nRT and if we want
to identify that gas we're probably
going to need the molar mass and molar
mass is grams per mole we have grams but
we don't have moles so let's solve for
it let's solve for n in the ideal gas
law so n is going to be equal to PV over
RT so now let's just plug in what we
know n or the number of moles in this
sample of gas are going to be equal to
one point zero zero atmospheres times
two point zero liters that's the volume
of the sample divided by the gas
constant R which in this case we're
going to use the version that is 0.0821
liters atmospheres per mole Kelvin
because we're going to want to cancel
out those other units and then the
temperature is 25 degrees Celsius but
remember we always want to express that
in Kelvin when we're doing calculations
so that is going to be 298 Kelvin and
then if we plug all that into the
calculator we get 0.08 to
so that is how many moles are in this
sample so now if we know the mass of
this sample of gas and we know how many
moles it represents all we have to do is
take the value in grams and divide by
the value in moles and we'll get grams
per mole so 1.31 grams over 0.08 two
moles is approximately 16 grams per mole
and now while this could be a few
different things we know it is a
hydrocarbon and so the only hydrocarbon
that is gonna have this molar mass is
gonna be methane because we need at
least one carbon atom that's 12 and then
we have no more room for a second one
and just add four hydrogen atoms on
there and we've gotten methane so this
gas must have been methane.